"Caffeine Shampoo and
Rosemary Oil for Hair Growth"
I’ve done videos
on drugs for hair growth,
supplements for hair growth,
and foods for hair growth.
What about natural options
that you can apply topically?
I ended my food video on this study,
suggesting consuming pumpkin seed oil
could increase hair growth.
What about just rubbing
it on your scalp?
It works in mice,
but what about men?
Or in this case, women:
pumpkin seed oil
(about a quarter teaspoon
rubbed onto the scalp once a day)
was tested head-to-head against
minoxidil foam (5 percent once a day)
for three months in women
with age-related pattern hair loss.
Both treatments worked,
but the drug worked better,
though at about five times the cost.
A similar experiment comparing a topical
0.2 percent caffeine solution,
which is about five times stronger
than coffee, with 5 percent minoxidil,
found they worked similarly well
for balding men,
though like in the
pumpkin seed oil trial
there was no third placebo group
to ensure they all weren’t just
somehow getting better on their own
(for example due
to seasonal influence,
with typically greater hair shedding
in the fall than the spring).
Dripping caffeine on human hair
follicles growing in a petri dish
enhances hair growth, and indeed,
when finally put to the test
against placebo won out for both
female and male pattern baldness,
with 85 percent satisfied
after unknowingly using
the caffeine-containing shampoo
for six months,
compared to only 36 percent
in the placebo shampoo group.
EGCG, one of the major constituents
of green tea,
also can promote human hair growth
in vitro and may help balding mice,
but I failed to find
any green tea clinical trials.
Pyrithione zinc shampoo,
typically used for dandruff,
beat out placebo for increasing hair
density in balding men after 26 weeks,
but not enough for the study subjects
to notice any difference,
working less than half
as well as the 5 percent minoxidil.
What about topical herbal treatments
used since time immemorial?
Ginger offers a good cautionary tale.
Ginger has a long history
of traditional use in Asia
to halt hair loss
and heighten hair growth.
Do a quick search for “ginger shampoo”
and turn up more than a thousand entries.
But when the
Natural Science Foundation of China
finally put it to the test,
researchers were surprised
it actually
suppressed human hair growth.
Given their results, they suggested
ginger could instead be used for
the removal of unwanted body hair.
Chinese knotweed, known in
traditional Chinese medicine circles
as He Shou Wu, is a flowering plant
in the buckwheat family
popularized as a hair tonic.
Like green tea, there are promising
in vitro and rodent studies,
but no human clinical trials.
Rosemary, however,
has been put to the test.
One hundred balding men
were randomized
to twice a day minoxidil
versus a rosemary lotion.
It took six months,
but eventually there were
significant comparable improvements
in hair counts in both groups.
The rosemary lotion appeared to work
as well as the drug.
You can make it at home by mixing
10 drops of rosemary essential oil
per fluid ounce
to your favorite lotion
and then rubbing a quarter teaspoon
onto your scalp twice a day.
That much rosemary oil would cost
about a penny a week.